{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Eleanor Billington and Susanna White were two of the four women charged with preparing for this event. James Baker claimed that this event occurred around Michaelmas. A governor ordered four of his men to go on a “fowling” mission three days before this event, which celebrated the provision of supplies by Massasoit. William Bradford organized this event after a successful corn harvest in 1621. For ten points, name this event in which the Plymouth Pilgrims held a feast of gratitude.",
      "answer": [
        "the First Plymouth Thanksgiving",
        "descriptions of the first Thanksgiving"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This country is of primary interest to the activist group Brothers to the Rescue, which had planes shot down in 1996. Edward Lansdale directed Operation Mongoose against this country, which was also the focus of the Helms-Burton Act. It sent numerous mental patients to the U.S. during the Mariel boatlift. The CIA trained Brigade 2506, which tried to invade this country in April 1961. For ten points, name this Caribbean island country, the site of the failed, U.S.-backed Bay of Pigs invasion.",
      "answer": "Republic of Cuba"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Latin term which became this economic phrase originated from the term for a head of cattle. The rate of return on this quantity being higher than the rate of growth in a country’s economy leads to inequality according to Thomas Piketty’s 2013 work describing “this concept” in the 21st Century. The exploitation of labor by the bourgeoisie was criticized in 1867 in an economic text by this name written by Karl Marx. For ten points, name this economic concept, a factor of production used to produce other goods.",
      "answer": [
        "capital",
        "Capital in the 21st Century",
        "Das Kapital",
        "capitalism until “quantity” is read in the second sentence"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In December 2016, this leader announced his country’s official unit of currency would become the Toman. This leader was elected in 2013 with the slogan of a “Government of prudence and hope” after Mahmoud Ahmadinejad served for two terms. This leader negotiated with the P5+1 countries regarding his country’s nuclear program, with a Joint Comprehensive Plan of Action agreed on in 2015. For ten points, name this current President of Iran.",
      "answer": "Hassan Rouhani"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. “Slick” Goodlin demanded $150,000 to perform this action, so the honor went to the second choice instead; that man fell off his horse and injured his ribs, so Jack Ridley fashioned a broom handle into a lever to help seal the hatch. This event, which took place above Rogers Dry Lake in the Mojave Desert, utilized the Bell XS-1, a rocket-powered airplane. For ten points, name this October 14, 1947 accomplishment performed by Chuck Yeager.",
      "answer": "first breaking of the sound barrier via airplane"
    },
    {
      "question": "A media building owned by this leader was rammed by a wheel-loader at the start of the Bulldozer Revolution. A Chinese embassy was accidentally bombed during a NATO intervention against this leader called Operation Allied Force. This man was accused of failing to prevent Ratko Mladic [m’lah-ditch] from perpetrating the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-neetz-ah] massacre by the prosecutors of his war crime trial, though he died of a heart attack in 2006 before a verdict could be reached. For ten points, name this Serbian president of Yugoslavia during the Kosovo War.",
      "answer": "Slobodan Milosevi´c"
    },
    {
      "question": "One work in this medium was paired with a verse calling the depicted figure a “Brobdingnagian Bagman.” Bags of money are rolled up a man’s tongue in an Honor´e Daumier work in this medium. A man straddles the continent of Africa while holding up a telegraph line in one of these works. The subject of another work in this medium is called the “Brains” for winning the Rochester National Convention and has his head replaced with a sack of money. Boss Tweed was often satirized by Thomas Nast in, for ten points, what type of editorial artwork?",
      "answer": "political cartoons"
    },
    {
      "question": "The arrest of an advocate of this cause inspired another advocate to sneak a knife into the National Gallery and slash the Rokeby Venus. A proponent of this cause was trampled to death in the Epsom Derby in 1913. The Cat and Mouse Act applied to people who were imprisoned for supporting this cause, whose advocates included Millicent Fawcett and several members of the Pankhurst family. For ten points, name this cause achieved in Great Britain in 1918, which effectively doubled the size of the country’s electorate.",
      "answer": "women’s suffrage in the United Kingdom"
    },
    {
      "question": "Along with two friends, the main character of this novel risks punishment by swimming naked across a canal in the middle of the night to rendezvous with three French women. This book’s protagonist feels remorse over a stabbing a man whom he discovers through his papers was a printer named Gerard Duval. In this novel, Kemmerich’s boots are acquired by the main character after the death of Fredrich Muller, and Kat’s death causes Paul Baumer to lose interest in fighting in World War I. For ten points, name this novel by Erich Maria Remarque.",
      "answer": "All Quiet on the Western Front or Im Westen nichts Neues"
    },
    {
      "question": "During these conflicts, the Thirteen Factories were twice destroyed. James Bremer used gunboats to great effect in this conflict and blockaded the Pearl River. The second of these conflicts began when the Arrow was seized. Lin Zexu sent a letter asking “where is your conscience?” to Queen Victoria in the first of these conflicts, which ended with the cessation of Hong Kong Island in the unequal Treaty of Nanking. For ten points, name this series of conflicts between Great Britain and China sparked by drug exports.",
      "answer": "First and/or Second Opium Wars"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The surrender of a fort in this state was demanded “In the name of the Great Jehovah and the Continental Congress!” A city in this state names a “conspiracy” defused by George Washington. A Revolutionary War battle in this state consisted of engagements at Freeman’s Farm and Bemis Heights and led to the surrender of John Burgoyne. For ten points, name this home state of Newburgh, Fort Ticonderoga, and Saratoga, as well as engagements on Manhattan Island.",
        "answer": "New York"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Fort Ticonderoga was the staging point for an invasion of Canada that was defeated at this 1775 battle, where Richard Montgomery was killed.",
        "answer": "Battle of Quebec City"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Laurens Janzoon Coster is alleged to have invented one method for producing these objects. Aldus Manutius and William Caxton were among the earliest producers of one type of these objects, examples of which produced before 1501 are called incunabula. These objects are typically in codex form, and the production of these objects was revolutionized in Mainz by improvements on metal moveable type. Manuscripts were quickly replaced by, for ten points, what bound objects, first mass produced by Johannes Gutenberg?",
        "answer": "printed books"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aldus Manutius was from this city, where Octavio Petruccio produced the first book of printed sheet music and were some 30% of the printers in Renaissance Italy worked. This city was excommunicated by Pope Paul V in 1606, mostly unrelated to its printing industry.",
        "answer": "Venice"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Edward Nkoloso trained people in this occupation by rolling them down hills in oil drums in Zambia. Yang Liwei’s work in this occupation as part of the Shenzhou project culminated in 2003. Ilan Ramon became the first Israeli citizen to carry out this job. In 1962, the citizens of Perth, Australia turned on their lights to honor an American in this occupation passing overhead. For ten points, name this occupation held by the Mercury Seven, including John Glenn.",
        "answer": [
          "astronauts",
          "Afronauts",
          "hang tian yuan",
          "yu hang yuan"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Chinese space program has currently launched two of these crafts named Tiangong with a third planned for the 2020s. In 2001, a Russian one of these crafts was intentionally de-orbited over Fiji.",
        "answer": "space station"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country, two rival partiess were nicknamed the Sharks and the Tailless. A revolt among tobacco planters in this country led to the assassination of its president, Ulises Heureaux [you-lee-zays ay-oh-rokes], in 1899. The Military Intelligence Service, or SIM, was a secret police force operated in this country by Johnny Abbes. Another leader of this country had three sisters of the Mirabal family assassinated in 1960 and notoriously executed people who pronounced the word “parsley” a certain way. For ten points, name this country once ruled by Rafael Trujillo that borders Haiti.",
        "answer": "Dominican Republic or Repu´blica Dominicana"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The word “parsley” in the aforementioned Parsley massacre served as this type of identifying phrase, as Trujillo’s forces differentiated Haitians from Dominicans by checking their pronunciation of the word. In the Book of Judges, this word was pronounced differently by the Ephraimites and Gileadites.",
        "answer": "shibboleth"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Royal Navy ship HMS Amethyst was trapped on this river for several months in 1949. A 1954 flood here devastated Hubei Province, and a series of canyons along its banks are the site of a project that displaced 1.3 million people and started producing power in 2003. This river is referred to in its native country as Chang Jiang. The Three Gorges Dam was built on, for ten points, what Chinese river that empties into the sea at Shanghai?",
        "answer": "Yangtze River or Chang Jiang before mention"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The baiji was a species of this animal that once dwelled in the Yangtze River. It was not found during a 2006 search and has been declared functionally extinct.",
        "answer": "river dolphin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This composer’s second piano concerto ends with a movement parodying Hanon exercises and was written for his son’s nineteenth birthday. This man wrote a piece in three days for the 37th anniversary of the October Revolution. This composer of the Festive Overture wrote another work that was described in the spurious memoir Testimony as a “parody of shrillness” and in Pravda as “A Soviet Artist’s Reply to Just Criticism.” For ten points, name this composer whose fifteen symphonies include the Leningrad.",
        "answer": "Dmitry Shostakovich"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shostakovich’s thirteenth symphony includes a setting of this Yevgeny Yevtushenko poem that commemorates a massacre of Ukrainian Jews during World War II.",
        "answer": "”Babi Yar”"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An inaugural address delivered by this U.S. president relates the story of soldier Martin Treptow, who died in World War I. Yellow ribbons were worn to celebrate the inauguration of this president. A speech delivered by this president to the National Association of Evangelicals claimed that the Judeo-Christian tradition was superior to the collective mentality of the Soviet Union, which he dubbed an “Evil Empire.” For ten points, name this president whose first inauguration coincided with the end of the Iran Hostage Crisis in 1980.",
        "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Reagan’s First Inaugural Address described Reagan’s political philosophy by saying that this concept “is not the solution to our problem;” this concept “is the problem.”",
        "answer": "government"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A stonemason named Elias of Dereham may have provided a building he designed with a copy of this document, which is to be read at cathedrals twice a year. This document exempted the seacoast from a stipulation calling for the removal of royal fish weirs. Shortly after this document’s adoption, a conflict that included a siege of Dover broke out. The First Barons’ War arose after the creation of, for ten points, what document that was sealed at Runnymede by King John in 1215?",
        "answer": [
          "Magna Carta Libertatum",
          "the Great Charter of the Liberties",
          "Magna Charta"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Stephen Langton, the holder of this post, helped write the Magna Carta.",
        "answer": "Archbishop of Canterbury"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Tecumseh",
      "prompt": "What...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President ended the Curse of Tecumseh by being elected in 1980 and not dying in office?",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle did Tecumseh die at, which shares its name with the river that flows through London?",
          "answer": "Battle of the Thames"
        },
        {
          "question": "War did he participate in to help stop an American invasion of Canada?",
          "answer": "War of 1812"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle did he lose to William Henry Harrison, who then incorporated it into a campaign slogan?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Tippecanoe",
            "Tippecanoe and Tyler Too"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Settlement, named after his brother, was that battle fought near?",
          "answer": "Prophetstown"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tribe was he a member of?",
          "answer": "Shawnee"
        },
        {
          "question": "State’s city of New Madrid names an earthquake he interpreted as a sign that he should fight the US?",
          "answer": "Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "Vice President claimed to have personally killed Tecumseh? This man was the only VP to have been chosen by the Senate under the Twelfth Amendment.",
          "answer": "Richard Mentor Johnson"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Medici Family",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Industry that was the source of the Medici wealth, as well as that of the Rothschild and Fugger families.",
          "answer": [
            "banking",
            "anything to do with finance"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "”Magnificent” member of the Medici family who patronized Botticelli and Michelangelo.",
          "answer": "Lorenzo the Magnificent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conspiracy that targeted Giuliano de Medici for death. It was sponsored by Sixtus IV.",
          "answer": "Pazzi Conspiracy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medici Queen of France, the wife of Henry II.",
          "answer": "Catherine de’ Medici"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name of the first Medici to control Florence, named the Elder, as well as the first Medici to be named Grand Duke of Tuscany.",
          "answer": "Cosimo de Medici"
        },
        {
          "question": "Revolt of unhappy wool workers put down by Salvestro de’ Medici.",
          "answer": "Revolt of the Ciompi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Patriarch of the Medici family who founded the family business and funded the family’s rise to power.",
          "answer": "Giovanni di Bicci de’ Medici"
        },
        {
          "question": "Medici Pope who evacuated Rome before its sack by Charles V. He oversaw the reaction to the English Reformation.",
          "answer": "Pope Clement VII"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Mexican Revolution",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Decade in which it took place, coinciding with World War I.",
          "answer": "1910s"
        },
        {
          "question": "Neighbor country whose diplomat, Henry Lane Wilson, was partially to blame.",
          "answer": [
            "United States of America",
            "USA",
            "America"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Religious organization that supported the overthrow of Francisco Madero and, much earlier, was targeted in La Reforma.",
          "answer": "Roman Catholic Church"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leader of the Division of the North who led a raid on Columbus, New Mexico.",
          "answer": [
            "Francisco “Pancho” Villa",
            "Jos´e Doroteo Arango Ar´ambula"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Harsh Mexican president who caused Woodrow Wilson to impose an arms embargo.",
          "answer": "Jos´e Victoriano Huerta M´arquez"
        },
        {
          "question": "Coup, named for its length, that overthrew Francisco Madero.",
          "answer": [
            "Ten Tragic Days",
            "La Decena Tr´agica"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President who was assassinated - or possibly committed suicide - after the Plan of Agua Prieta forced him from power.",
          "answer": "Venustiano Carranza"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle in which Alvaro Obregon’s Constitutionalists defeated the numerically superior Division of the North.",
          "answer": "Battle of Celaya"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2002, Isioma Daniel became the subject of one of these works after joking about the Miss World beauty pageant. Creators of these declarations are known as (20 pts)",
        "muftis, though there is no international body to decide fiqh [feek] controversies over these declarations. (10 pts)",
        "Osama bin Laden issued two of these statements prior to becoming head of al-Qaeda. For ten points, give this term for a legal opinion delivered by an Islamic jurist, one of which was delivered by Ayatollah Khomeini in 1989 authorizing the murder of Salman Rushdie for publishing The Satanic Verses."
      ],
      "answer": "fatwas or fatawa"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description acceptable. Arthur Chapman served as the translator of this oration. This speech declares “It is the young men who say yes and no” and describes how “little children are freezing to death” and how some people “have run away to the hills;” its speaker comments “Maybe I shall find them among the dead.” This speech was given after a (20 pts)",
        "loss at the Battle of Bear Paw Mountain in 1877 forced its speaker to capitulate to Oliver Howard. This speech ends with a declaration made “from (10 pts)",
        "where the sun now stands” by a speaker whose “heart is sick and sad.” For ten points, name this speech given by a chief of the Nez Perce, noting the end of his war against the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Chief Joseph’s surrender speech or the “I Will Fight No More Forever” speech",
        "descriptive answers relating to Chief Joseph surrendering",
        "Nez Perce surrender speech before “Nez Perce” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man declared that “we should not emulate [Germany] only in armaments” in support of the National Insurance Act. This man advocated for war to protect national honor in his Mansion House Speech, given in response to the (20 pts)",
        "Agadir Crisis. He heavily increased a land tax to fund welfare programs in his “People’s Budget,” and this leader’s foreign minister advocated for the “establishment...of a national home of the (10 pts)",
        "Jewish people” in the Balfour Declaration. For ten points, name this Welsh prime minister who led Britain through World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "David Lloyd George"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was blocked from command by Publius Sulpicius Rufus and was opposed in Hispania by Quintus Sertorius. He defeated his rival, Archelaus, at both Chaeronea and Orchomenus during the First (20 pts)",
        "Mithridatic War. This ruler, who was awarded a grass crown for his bravery in the Social War and captured Jugurtha during a campaign in (10 pts)",
        "Numidia, began the practice of targeting political opponents with proscription. For ten points, name this Roman dictator who began the era of civil wars by defeating Gaius Marius."
      ],
      "answer": "Lucius Cornelius Sulla"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The wife of one participant in this event was enraged to see publicity photos showing the mistress Veronica Porch´e. Eddie Futch told Carlos Padilla to end this event, whose eventual winner claimed he lost five pounds of weight during it. The (20 pts)",
        "“rope-a-dope” strategy was ineffective early in this event, which took place in oppressively hot and humid conditions. The winner had angered the loser in pre-fight banter by calling him “The (10 pts)",
        "Gorilla”. For ten points, name this third and final match between Muhammad Ali and Joe Frazier, fought in 1975 in the Philippines."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Thrilla in Manila",
        "descriptions of the third and/or final fight between Ali and Frazier, with names in either order, until “Muhammad” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) At the first of these events, a participant was described as a “hatchet man” after declaring that 1.6 million Americans had been killed in “Democrat wars.” At a later one of these events, the opening statement “Who am (20 pts)",
        "I? Why am I here?” was given by Admiral James Stockdale. A participant in another of these events said “that was really uncalled for, Senator” after being told, (10 pts)",
        "“you’re no Jack Kennedy.” For ten points, name these televised events that have been contested between Bob Dole and Walter Mondale, Lloyd Bentsen and Dan Quayle, and more recently, Tim Kaine and Mike Pence."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Vice-Presidential debates",
        "descriptive answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The USS Panay sank after evacuating survivors from this city. Prince Asuka was given immunity for events in this city, which was captured by the army of Matsui Iwane. A (20 pts)",
        "safe zone in this city was created by John Rabe, a German businessman, saving thousands of lives. This capital of the Taiping Heavenly Kingdom and the (10 pts)",
        "Republic of China was the site of a contest to kill 100 civilians with a sword and other such war crimes. For ten points, name this Chinese city that, in 1937, was subjected to a “rape” by invading Japanese forces."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nanking or Nanjing",
        "descriptions of the Rape of Nanking",
        "Nanjing"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Faith Ringgold painted this object, covered with names like Malcolm X and Harriet Tubman, in Freedom of Speech. An image captioned “We the People” by Shepard Fairey shows this object’s design being worn on a (20 pts)",
        "hijab. Another artist used newspaper and encaustic to create a completely white version of this object in 1955. A photograph by (10 pts)",
        "Joe Rosenthal features this object being hoisted by six Marines. Jasper Johns showed only 48 stars on, for ten points, what national symbol that was raised after the Battle of Iwo Jima?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "American flag",
        "any description of the flag of the United States of America",
        "prompt on partial answers"
      ]
    }
  ]
}